<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Cayphas and asked them what was prosylyte. And</title>
            <title>Gospel of Nicodemus.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1529</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 70 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08234</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18569</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S105413</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99841141</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99841141</idno>
            <idno type="VID">5702</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08234)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 5702)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 303:04)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Cayphas and asked them what was prosylyte. And</title>
                  <title>Gospel of Nicodemus.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[40+] p. : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>In Poules chyrche yarde by me John Skot,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Imprynted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>In the yere of our lorde god. M.CCCCC.xxix. the .vi. day of Apriell.] [1529]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>An edition of: The gospel of Nicodemus.</note>
                  <note>Title from first line of text, penultimate leaf of quire A.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴(-A1,2?) B⁴ C⁶ D-E⁴.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect; lacks all before last two leaves of quire A.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Gospel of Nicodemus --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:5702:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:5702:1"/>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <p>Cayphas and aſked them what was proſylyte. And they ſayd that proſelyty was paynyms chyldren / and ſo be his dyſcyples / &amp; for that they ſay that he is borne in fornycacyon. Than anſwered theſe .xii. men whoſe names were ſuche. Lazarus. Aſtorius. Antonius. Ia<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cob. Seriꝰ. Gamaliel. Iſaak. Fyues. Azariꝰ. Agrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pa. Amenus / and Iudas. We ſaye that we ne are pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſelyty / but we be Iewes chyldren / and we ſay trouth that we were there as Ioſeph wedded Mary. Than called Pylate theſe .xii. men that ſayd thus / &amp; he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iured them by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hyght of holy Cezar yf that he were not borne i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fornycacyon that ye bere wytnes &amp; ſurete &amp; ſwere before all this people. And theſe .xii. men an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered to Pylate and ſayd we haue be our lawe that we ne ought to ſwere for it is ſyn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e / but we wyl ſwe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re by holy Cezar / yf it be not as we ſay we wyl be cul<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pable of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deth. we ſe wel y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Ieſu is not borne in forny<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cacyon to be byleued by theyr worde. And we ſaye all ſayd y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> other that he is borne in fornycacyon / and that he is an euyil werker. And thus he ſayth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he is god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des ſone and therto a kynge / &amp; yet thou wylt not byle<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue vs that haue the lawe to kepe. Than commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded Pylate that all ſholde go out of the parlore ſaue theſe xii. men that ſayd that our lord was not borne i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> forny<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cacyon / &amp; alſo he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded that our lorde Ieſu ſholde be ledde out vnto that one ſyde of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> parlore. Than ſaid Pylate to the ſe .xii. men. For what cauſe is it y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> they wyll brynge Ieſu to deth. And they anſwered &amp; ſayd that the mayſters of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lawe had hym in hate bycauſe that he heled maladyes and ſykeneſſes vpon the Sa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bot daye. Than ſayd Pylate. A I ſe well for his good werkes they wyll ſlee hym. Than wente Pylate out of the parlore full of heuynes and ſayd to all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iewes
<pb facs="tcp:5702:2"/>I haue wytneſſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I can fynde in this man no poynt of deth. The Iewes anſwered / yf he had neuer be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> an euyll doer we ne had not delyuered hym to the. Than ſayd Pylate to the Iewes. what ſayd god that there ſholde be no man ſlayne but of me. Than eatred Pyla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te in to the parlore agayne / and called our lorde Ieſu to hym &amp; ſayd. Thou arte kynge of Iewes. Our lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de Ieſu anſwered agayne / thou ſayeſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> of thy ſelfe or elles other haue ſayd that to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> of me. Than ſaid Py<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>late vnto our lorde Ieſu cryſt. Thou w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>eſt wel that I am no Iewe but of thyne owne nacyon / y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> byſſhop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes and prynces haue delyuered y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> to me / but I wote neuer what euyll thou haſt done them / yf thou be kyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge of Iewes anſwere to me. Oure lorde anſwered to hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> my kyngdome is not in this worlde / for yf my kyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gedome were in this worlde my mynyſters wold not be ayenſt me / nor I ſholde not haue be delyuered to the but my kyngedome is not now here. Than anſwered Pylate / than I ſe wel thou arte a kyng. Than anſwe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red our lord Ieſu / thou ſayeſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> I am a kynge / and to that I was borne / and for to declare to the world that who ſo be of trouth wyll here my worde. Than ſayde Pylate what is trouth by thy worde there is but ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell trouth in the worlde. Our lord ſayd to Pylate / vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>derſtande trouth how y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> it is Iuged in erth of that y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> dwell therin. And thus ſayd Pylate to the Iewes I haue wytneſſe bothe in heuen and in erthe / ſonne and m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ne that I can fynde no cauſe of dethe in this man. Than a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſwered the Iewes / is not this a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>grete cauſe that he ſayth of our temple / that he myght dyſtroye it and reyſe it agayne in thre dayes. Than ſayd Pylate what temple is that the whiche ye ſpeke of. And the Iewes anſwered that it was the temple of Salamo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb facs="tcp:5702:2"/>the whiche was in edyfyenge .xivii. yere / &amp; this Ihe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus ſayd that he wolde dyſtroy it / and reyſe it agayn in thre dayes. I am ſayd Pylate without gylte of ſpyl<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lynge of this mannes blode / and that ſhall ye well ſe what wyll ye do with hym. The ie wes that were ful of enuy cryed all with one voyce / the ſhedynge of his blode vpon vs and vpon our chyldren.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ How Pylate toke of the mooſt auncyent men of the lawe / as byſſhoppes &amp; other mayſters to counſeyle.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <head>
                        <list>
                           <item>Cayphas.</item>
                           <item>Pylate.</item>
                           <item>Annas.</item>
                        </list>
                     </head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <p>THan Pylate toke of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mooſt auncyent men as byſſhoppes and mayſters of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lawe and ſayd. Syrs do not ayenſt this ſymple man for I doo you to
<pb facs="tcp:5702:3"/>wete that he is not worthy to be deed / is not he more worthy that hath heled maladyes tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he had broke y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſabbot daye. Than ſayd y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iewes a good Iuge take hede yf ony ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hath done a forfayte ayenſt Cezar / we<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re he not worthy to be deed. And tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Pylate ſayd vnto them yes. Tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſayd y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iewes moche more is he wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> forfayteth ayenſt god / for he ſayd hym ſelfe that he is goddes ſone / for whan we coniured hym that he ſholde tell vs yf he were goddes ſone or not / he deny. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> it not / &amp; yet he ſayd y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we ſholde ſe the ſone of man<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tynge vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ryght hande of the godhede / comynge out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſkyes of heuen. And whan Pylate herde thus he ledde oure lorde Ieſu vpon that other parte of the parlore &amp; ſayd to hym. Man I ne wote what I maye do with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>. Than ſayd our lorde Ieſu to Pylate. Moy ſes and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prophetes here before preched of my paſſyon &amp; of my reſurteccyon. Whan Pylate herde this he ꝓ nounced all the wordes of our lorde to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iewes. And anone the Iewes ſayd to Pylate. What woldeſt tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> here more of his fals felau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der. Tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſayd Pylate take hym i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to your ſynagoge / and deme there on hym your lawe. The Iewes anſwere / our lawe commaundeth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> yf ony man ſyn or treſpaſſe ayenſt ony man he ſhall withdra we hym .xiii. dayes out of the temple. And he y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſynneth or treſpaſſeth ayenſt god by ſlaunder / oure Iawe biddeth that he ſhal be ſtoned to deth. And for as moche as Ieſus ſayth that he ſhall ſyt in heuen vpon the ryght ſyde of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deuyne mageſte / and that he ſhall come frome heuen in to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſkyes / for this ſclannder we wyll that he be crucyfyed. Than ſayd Pylate y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> is not good that ye caſt you for to do. And than Pylate loked aboute hym &amp; ſawe many men &amp; women that wepte ſore / and helde theyr countenaunce vpon hym. Than
<pb facs="tcp:5702:3"/>vnder Cezare the Emperour. Whan y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iewes herde this than they ſayd to Nychodemus. ye take thou the trouth of Ieſu / and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thou may haue thy dwellynge place w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hym. Than lyfte vp Nychodemꝰ his handes to heuen &amp; ſayd. God grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t that I may haue parte of the trouth of Ieſu / &amp; a dwellyng place myght I haue of hym. God grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te that it may be ſo as ye haue ſayd</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ How certayne Iewes ſhewed to Pylate the myracles that Chryſte had done.❀</head>
               <p>ANd anone there ſtarte forth a Iewe afore Py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late / and thus he ſayd. My lord Pylate I ſay beddred .xxxviii. yere / &amp; euery day for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſt parte in peryll of deth / &amp; ſo it befell that my lord Ieſu came by me and had pyte on me / and than he had me take my bedde and go home i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to my hous / and anone with his wordes I was made hole. And anone after came an other Iewe afore Pylate and thus he ſayd. My lorde Pylate I was poore blynde / as my lorde Ieſu paſſed afore me I ſayd to hym Ieſu the ſone of Dauyd haue mercy on me. And he had mercy on me / and he put his hande to myne eyen &amp; than I ſawe. And than another Iewe that ſtode afore Pylate ſayd. Syr I was a me fell &amp; my lord Ieſu cryſt made me hole with his wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de. After that came an aged woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> afore Pylate and fayd my lorde Pylate I was dyſeaſed with the reed flyx thre pere and more / and Idyd not but touche the hemme of the veſture of my lorde Ieſu / and anone I was made hole of my malady / &amp; therfore / my lorde py<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>late haue mercy on hym / and do hym not to deth. And whan Pylate herde this he fered. And anone a grete company of Iewes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> our lorde Ieſu had heled cryed
<pb facs="tcp:5702:4"/>all with one voyce. A grete ſauyour of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people is our lorde Ieſu. whan Pylate herde this he ſayd vnto Cay phas &amp; Annas / and other mayſters of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lawe. I mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uayle why y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> your forne faders prynces &amp; byſſhoppes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lawe heled not men of theyr infyrmytes / as this man doth. And they anſwered no worde therto. And theſe men y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> our lorde had heled cryed with one voyce Our bleſſyd lorde Ieſu hath wrought many dyuyne myracles / as he y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> reyſed Lazar fro dethe to lyfe whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che had layen deed foure dayes in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> erth / and our lord Ieſu by the vertue of his wordes reyſed hym out of his moment &amp; brought hym a lyue amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge vs &amp; his ſy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſters / &amp; made hym to ſyt with hym at his table. Wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Pylate herde this he was all abaſſhed for fere &amp; cryed with an hygh voyce to the Iewes &amp; ſayd. Men what is this that ye wyldo. Iſe that without gylte ye wyl ſhedde the blode of hym that hath nothynge wrought amyſſe. Than roſe Pylate vp &amp; toke Nychodemus to hym &amp; theſe .xii. men whiche that ſayd that our lorde was not borne in fornycacyon / &amp; thus he ſayd to them Syrs I haue grete affeccyon in you / tel me what I ſhall do with hym. And they ſayd ſyr we can not ſaye but we wyll neuer aſſeut to the wyll of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mayſters of the lawe nor to theyr werkes / and therfore let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſe wel to theyr ſoules that they may be ſaued at the day of Iugement. Than turned Pylate to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mayſters of the lawe &amp; to the other Iewes and ſayd thus to them Syrs ye knowe well that it is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cuſtome amonge vs to delyuer a pryſonere to the people for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> loue of our ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bot y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hye daye of ſacryfyce / &amp; ſyrs ye know well that I haue i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> my pryſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a noble pryloner a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſleer whiche is worthy to be deed / whoſe name is Barabas / wyll ye that I delyuer you hym or elles Ieſu whiche is w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:5702:4"/>out gylte &amp; not worthy to dye. The prynces and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> byf ſhoppes and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> olde men they ſayd with one voyce we wyll that thou delyuer to vs Barabas. Tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſayd Py<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>late what wyll ye than ſay that I do with Ieſu whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che is called cryft. Than ſayd y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iewes w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> an hye voy ce / let hym be crucyfyed / &amp; ſome ſayd yf thou let hym go thus / thou ne arte Cezars frende ſyth that he laid this foule ſclau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der that he is goddes ſone / and therto a kynge / for who ſo euer ſayd y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he is a kynge / he ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth ayenſt Cezare. And whan that Pylate herd this he was wonders heuy / and thus he ſayd to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iewes all dayes from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> begynnynge ye haue be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>traryous to them y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> haue done well to you / &amp; to hym ye haue do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne moche harme &amp; moche turmentynge. Than ſayd y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iewes what is he y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hath done ſo moche good to vs Than ſayd Pylate our god whiche hath holpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you &amp; delyuered you out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> handes of Egypte which drow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned your enemyes in the depneſſe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reed ſee &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>edde you thrughe the water of the ſee alſo drye as vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de. And alſo in deſerte he reyned vnto you ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>na and made water come out of the harde ſtone in deſert whiche that ye dranke of &amp; all your beeſtes. And alſo he gaue to you the .x. co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dementes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lawe. And in all theſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dementes that he hath charged you with ye haue ben contraryous to your god. As whan ye made a calfe to be your god / whiche wold haue dyſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>heryted you &amp; dyſtroyed you ne had Moyſes be your mayſter / that prayed to your god for you for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> peryl y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ye were in / &amp; now ye ſaye to me that I hate my kyng &amp; am not his frende yf I delyuer not this man Ieſus that hath cured moche of your people of many if yrmy tyes whiche is your kynge that neuer dyde euyll but euer moche goodneſſe and profyte. Whan the Iewes
<pb facs="tcp:5702:5"/>herd this they were full of anger &amp; maltalent / &amp; thus they cryed all togyder &amp; ſayd. Our kyng is Cezarem perour of Rome. For we know wel y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Ieſꝰ is no kyng though y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> kyngꝭ ſought hym in Bedlem &amp; ſayd y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> they ſought y kynge of Iewes / &amp; offred to hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> gyftes / but yet is he thertore no kyng / we knowe well y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> He rode herde ſay that they ſought y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kyng of Iewes / he wold haue ſlayne hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> therfore. And ſo he dyd ſlee thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſandes or chyldren therfore in Bedlem &amp; all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tre a bout / as we haue ſayd to you here before. wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Pylate herde this he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be ſtyl / &amp; tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſayd to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. A is it not he tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Herode ſought for to ſlee. And y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iewes anſwered &amp; ſayd y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it was he. And anone Pyla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te dyd co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded water to be brought to hym / &amp; afore the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all he waſſhed his ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des ſayng thꝰ. I am not gyl<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ty of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpylly<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge of this ryghtful ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes blode &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> may you well ſe / but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> blode of hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be vpon you &amp; vpon your chyldren. Than co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded Pylate y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> a grete co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany of knyghtes ſholde be brought afore hym to his parlore. And tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Pyſate caſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tence vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our lord Ieſu cryſt and thus he ſayd to hym.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ How Pylate co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the Iewes y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> no bylay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes ſhold put Ieſu cryſte to his paſſyon but knygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes.</head>
               <figure/>
               <p>THyne owne people hath dyſpreued all that euer I haue ſpoken for the / and therfore I co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunde at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> begynnynge y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> lay ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des on hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> but yf he be a knyghte / or
<pb facs="tcp:5702:5"/>elles of gentyll blode / for it is not ſyttynge that a kyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge ſholde be ſlayne of vylaynes / &amp; therfore I co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de that at the fyrſt begynnynge that he be ſcourged to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pleaſynge of the fyrſt prynces / and than lyfte hym vp vpon the croſſe / and with hym two theues the whiche that hath beneuyll doers / that one by name <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>yſmas and that other Geſmas / and lette them be ſlayne with vyllaynes / and no gentylles to touche them. And tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our lorde Ieſu was ledde out of the parlore / and the two theues with hym / and than they lebde them in to another parlore / wherin was a pyller of whyte mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble / and there they dyſpoyled our lord Ieſu out of his clothes / and bounde hym naked vnto the pyller / and there they bete hym and ſcourged hym with yerds &amp; whyppes / ſoo hugely that there was no ſkynne hole vpon hym / and that was a pyteful ſyght for to ſe that bleſſyd body ſtandynge all naked before all the people ſcornynge &amp; ſayenge thus to our lord god in his ſcour<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gyng / do gladly our kynge for this is our fyrſt begyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nynge. And than the mayſters of the lawe ſayd to the knyghtes / do on our kyng a ſofte garme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t and let vs crowne hym for our kynge. And than y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> knyghtes dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de vpon hym a clothe of ſylke whiche for haboundau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of blode was ſo clonge to hym / that at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pullynge of it was an hondred folde more payne to hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> than was his ſcourgynge. And whan they had pulled of this gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment they dyde on hym a reed man tell of ſylke / and af<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter that they ſet a garlande of thornes vpon his heed / &amp; they preſſed ſoo ſore y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> garlande of thornes vpon his heed that the thornes perced downe in to his brayne &amp; ſoo at the laſte they ledde hym to the croſſe / and there they crucyfyed hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> bytwene two theues. Dyſmas an the ryght ſyde / and Gelmas on the lefte ſyde. And ſo
<pb facs="tcp:5702:6"/>they put to his mouth a ſponge full of azell and gall a that they put to his mouth for to drynke of. And thus that bleſſyd lorde Ieſu ſuffred all that euer they wold doo to hym. And than our lorde Ieſu loked vp to the fader and ſayd thus. My fader forgyue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pace / for they ne wote what they do / &amp; than y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> knygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes keſt lottes vpon his veſture for to wete who ſhold haue it / and than the prynces of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lawe with byſthop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes and many other / they cryed vnto oure lorde Ieſu and thus they ſayd. Thou haſt heled many other / and thou ne mayſt hele thy ſelfe / yf thou be goddes ſone co<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me downe of the croſſe and we ſhal byleue on the. And tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſayd y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> knyghtes in ſcorne yf y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> be kyng of Iewes delyuer now thy ſelfe. And than was co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded that a knyghte ſholde be broughte forthe whoſe name was Longeus / and hym they made to put a ſpere to Ieſus ſyde. This knyght Longeus was blynde / and ſo the prynces of the lawe made hym for to perce our lordes ſyde &amp; ſo there came out of his ſyde bothe blode &amp; wa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter / &amp; ſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> blode came re<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nyng downe by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpere ſhafte vnto Longeus hande / and he by auenture wyped his eyen with his hande / and anone he dyde ſe.❀</p>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Nd than Pylate dyde wryte a bylle vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whiche was wryten. Ieſus nazarenus rex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tudeorum. That is for to ſaye. Ieſus of Na<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>zareth kynge of Ieſus. And this was wry<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ten in hebre we / greke / and latyn. And this tytle they put aboue his heed vpon the croſſe. Than Geſmas the thefe whiche henge on the lefte ſyde of our lorde ſayde thus to our lorde Ieſu / yf thou be god delyuer bothe the and vs. Than Dyſmas that henge on the tyghte ſyde of our lorde Ieſu blamed hym for his wordes &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:5702:6"/>thus he ſayd to hym. It ſemeth by thy wordes that y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> dredeſt not god nor byleueſt not in hym / and therfore thou arte endleſly dampned / for wel thou woteſt that we haue deſerued that we ſuffre deth / but he hath ry<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ght nought forfayted nor myſdone / and without deler uynge he is brought here to. And whan Dyſmas had ſayd theſe wordes he loked vpon Ieſu cryſt and thus he ſayd to hym. Lorde Ieſu haue mercy vpon me wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou comeſt in to thy kyngdome. And than anſwered Ieſus vnto hym and ſayd. This daye ſhalte thou be with me in Paradyce / &amp; that tyme was aboute myd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daye / and fro this tyme vnto none of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> daye the ſonne was hydde and loſt his bryghtnes / and the vayle of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> temple was ſmyten downe to the grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de in two par<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyes and ſome men ſaye that an au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gell dyde it with a trace of fyre. And this au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gel ſayd many one heryng I am wytneſſe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> paſſyon of Ieſu Cryſt. After that our lorde Ieſu cryſte cryed with an hyghe voyce and ſayde. Fader in to thy handes I be take my ſpyryte / &amp; than he yelded vp his ſoule vnto his fader. And whan Centurio that was prynce ouer the Iewes / and Con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtable in lyke wyſe ſaw theſe tokens that were be fall he gloryfyed god &amp; ſayd / forſoth this man was ryght full / and that is wel ſeen by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tokens that are be falle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> And ſoo all the people that were there as good folkes whan the ſawe theſe werkes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vertue of our lozde they ſmote the yrbreſtes with theyr handes.❀</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ Howe Centurio tolde Pylate of the wonders that was at Chryſtes paſſyon / and the ſame Pylate tolde the Iewes therof / and of the precyous cloth that our lorde was buryed in.❀</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:5702:7"/>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <head>
                        <list>
                           <item>Cayphas.</item>
                           <item>Pylate.</item>
                           <item>Centurio.</item>
                        </list>
                     </head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Nd Centurio tolde to Pylate all that was be fall. And wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Pylate herde this he was wonders heuy and lory / and ſo for foryneſſe and heuyneſſe he ne ete nor dra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ke that daye Than called Pylate the Iewes / and thus he ſayde to them. Meruayle ye not of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tokens that here be falle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at the paſſyon of Ieſu / and that the ſonne loſte his ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ght and alſo the day. And the Iewes ſayd to Pylate. Syrit was the clypſe of the ſonne as we haue vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanden of wyſe men afore vs. Tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſayd Pylate how may it be that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vayle of the te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple is ſmyten a ſonder and many graues vndone / &amp; deed men ryſe vp frome deth to lyfe / hath y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> clypſe of the ſone done all this. All theſe tokens men tell me are befalle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the cyte of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem / &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:5702:7"/>yf ye byleue not me aſke Centurio / &amp; they that were with hym whiche kepte Ieſu. Than were theſe men brought forthe afore y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iewes whiche that bare wytneſſe / &amp; thus they ſayd. Forſothe we ſaye y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> in the dyenge of Ieſu the erth groned &amp; ſhoke as a wa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter doth whan it is meued / &amp; we ſame that many bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyes aroſe frodeth to lyfe / &amp; by theſe toke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s we byleue that this Ieſus is goddes ſone. Than y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> apoſtles and holy women that had folowed our forde Ieſu fro Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lylee / ſawe that was befallen &amp; that men had done to hym dre we them by them ſelfe. Than Ioſeph of Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mathy keſt hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for to by a precyous clothe for to wynde our lorde Ieſu in whan he myght gete grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te of Py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late for to haue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> body. And on thꝭ wyſe came Ioſeph by this precyous cloth as ye ſhall here. ¶ There was a knyȝt of Capharnane whoſe name was Leuy / this knyght wedded a yonge lady / and by proceſſe of tyme they had togyder a doughter / whom they called Syn donia and her they put to lernynge / &amp; ſo by proceſſe of tyme ſhe wexed a curyoꝰ werker / as of clothes of gol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de and clothes of ſylke / and of all other womens wer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes. And ſo at the laſt wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> god wold this Leuy dyed and than his wyfe for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> grete loue that ſhe loued hym ſhe fell in to a grete malady as in a palſey / ſo ferforth that ſhe myght neyther ſtere hande nor fote / and ſo for this grete ſekenes ſhe fell ia gret pouerte ſo ferforth that ſhe ne had to lyue vpon / but vy the werke of her doughters handes. And ſo it befel that vpon the ſame daye that our lorde Ieſu was deed this lady ſayde to her doughter. My dou ghter Syndonia thou knoweſt well that our grete ſabbot day is nere / than muſt we ete our paſke lambe / &amp; on this daye is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> grete market at Barmathye / therfore good doughter go and araye
<pb facs="tcp:5702:8"/>the / &amp; take ſome of thy werke that thou haſt wrought and bye vs there ſuche thynges as is nedeful to the &amp; me at this holy tyme. Her doughter Sindonia anſwe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red to her moder and ſayd / moder your wyll ſhal be do ne / and moder I doo you to vnderſtande that I haue wrought the curyouſeſt cloth that euer was made / for it fell ſo grac youſly to werke that it is more curyous than I can ſkyl of / and than y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lady ſayd to her dough<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter lette me ſe that clothe / and Syndonia ſhe wed this cloth to her moder. And wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this lady ſaw this cloth ſhe ſayd thus. Bleſſyd be that lorde that hath made y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> to werke ſuche a cloth / and doughter vpon my bleſſyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge ſell it to no man but yf he tell the what he ſhall do withall. And than this mayde Syndonia waſſhed &amp; bawmed her / and arayed her to the market / and in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> market ſtode Ioſeph of Barmathye with moche peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſpekynge of our lordes deth / and by auenture this mayde Syndonia came before hym / &amp; Ioſeph of Bar mathye eſpyed y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> clothe that hanged on her arme / and aſked her yf ſhe wold ſel that cloth. And ſhe anſwered and ſayde ye ſyr. And than Ioſeph aſked her y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pryce &amp; ſhe ſayde .xxx. beſauntes. And anone Ioſeph payed to her .xxx. beſauntes. And Syndonia fell downe to his fete prayeng hym y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he wolde tell her what he ſholde do withall. And than he anſwered her &amp; ſayd. Dough<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter this daye is deed an holy prophete that men called Ieſus of Nazareth / and that holy ꝓphete Ipurpoſe for to bury &amp; wynde in this cloth / doughter now haue I tolde y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> what Iwyll do withall / and therfore tel me who made this cloth that I haue bought of the. And this mayde ſayd that her ſelfe made it. And Ioſeph aſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ked her what was her name / and ſhe ſayd Syndonia Than ſayd Ioſeph now after you I ſhall name this
<pb facs="tcp:5702:8"/>cloth for this cloth ſhall be named Syndonia / &amp; than this mayde wente home to her moder &amp; tolde her how ſhe had ſpedde / and her moder aſked her what ſhold be done with the cloth. And Syndonia tolde her that the holy prophete that was y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> tyme deed ſholde be buryed therin. And who ſhall bury hym therin ſayd this lady And Syndonia ſayd y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Ioſeph of Barmathye ſholde burye hym therin. And wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this lady herde this ſhe ſayd thus. Wolde my lorde god &amp; that prophete that I had gyuen that cloth to his buryeng. And anone with that word ſhe was more holer tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> euer ſhe was afore And anone y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lady and her doughter fell downe to the grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de vpon theyr knees thank ynge our lorde god of this glorious myracle. And ſo afterwarde our lord ga<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue them ſuche grace that the moder was wedded to a worthy duke / &amp; her doughter was Empreſſe of Rome And ſo they lyued euer after in our lordes ſeruyce / &amp; wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Ioſeph of barmathye had bought / this precyous cloth whiche was lorde &amp; Conſtable ouer all Pylates me / he was a full good man &amp; a ryghtful / he was not aſſented to the accuſacyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s and wordes of the Iewes he abode y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kyngdome of god / &amp; ſo he came to Pylate &amp; aſked hym the body of Ieſu. And Pylate grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it. Than this Ioſeph &amp; Nychodemus toke downe the body of Ieſu of the croſſe / and hym he wounde in this Sindonia that he had bought / &amp; he buryed him in his monument / where as neuer man was buryed in &amp; ſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iewes wolde haue ſlayne Ioſeph &amp; the .xii. men y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> had ſpoken for our lorde Ieſu afore Pylate. And alſo they wolde haue ſlayne Nychodemus / &amp; alſo thoſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> our lorde had made hole of many grete infyrmytes and alſon they had dyſcouered afore Pylate all his good werkes that he had done in euery place.❀</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:5702:9"/>
               <head>¶ How the Iewes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſpyred euyll agaynſt Nychode mus and Ioſeph / and of many other meruayles.</head>
               <figure/>
               <p>THAN Nicho demꝰ. we wed hi ſelfe to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Ie<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wes / hicauſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> he was theyr prynce &amp; theyr guyde / &amp; ſone after there ga<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dered a grete multytude of Iewes in toy<hi rend="sup">e</hi> te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple afore Ny chodemꝰ / and thus he ſaid to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. How may this be that ye are entred i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to this holy te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple whiche haue your hanoes blody of the dethe of Ieſu that ryghtfull man whom ye haue vntruly crucyfyed. Than anſwe red to Nychodemus / Annas &amp; Cayphas / Symeon &amp; Datan / Gamaliei / Iudas / Leuy / Neptalim / &amp; all the other Iewes / how arte thou ſo hardy to come amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge vs that arte conſentynge to Ieſu / and therfore ſuche parte as he hath muſt thou haue with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> in this worl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de. Than anſwered Nychodemus and ſayd. A men y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> peas of Ieſu be with me in this worlde / and in that other endleſly. And y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iewes anſwered &amp; ſayd. A men
<pb facs="tcp:5702:9"/>And as Nichodemꝰ had a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſwered thus / came Ioſeph of Barmathye amonge them &amp; ſayd thus to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iewes why be ye beuy to me w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> maletale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te for Iaſked y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> body of Ieſu of Pylate / and Ido you to were y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I haue bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in my newe monume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t / &amp; wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de hym in a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyous clothe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> is called Syndonia. And I ſay to you that ye haue wrought euyll &amp; ſynfully y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ye haue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truly crucyfyed Ieſu without deſeruynge / &amp; alſo ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lycyouſly ye ꝑſed his ſyde w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a ſpere / &amp; wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iewes herd this they toke Ioſeph &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be kept well &amp; thus they ſayd to Ioſeph. we knowe well y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> arte not worthy to haue a buryenge place amonge vs for we ſhal gyue thy fleſſhe &amp; careyne to wylde beſtes &amp; wylde foules / and to be deuoured w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> houndes. Than Ioſeph ſayd to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theſe wordes / ye be lyke to proude Golyas as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prophete ſayth / to me lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geth vengeau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce &amp; I ſhal yelde it ſayth god. And yet wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Pylate waſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhed his ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des &amp; ſayd I am vngylty of this mannes blode ſhedyng / he anſwered &amp; ſayd / y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> blode of hym be on vs &amp; on our chyldren / wete it well that fro y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tyme forwarde ſhall y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wrath of god come vpon you &amp; vpon your chyldren as your ſelfe ſayd / &amp; wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iewes her de this they were ryght angry / &amp; put Ioſeph in a der<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke pryſon &amp; ſhyt the dore ſtrongly &amp; put therto kepers. Than Annas &amp; Cayphas and other byſſhoppes of the lawe / keſt for to aſſemble them after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſabbot daye for to ſlee Ioſeph / &amp; whan they were aſſembled they ſent to the pryſon and vndyde the dore / but they founde not Ioſeph therin / wherfore they were fore abaſſhed.</p>
               <p>¶ Howe one of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> knyghtes that kepte the ſepulcre of our lord came and tolde the mayſters of the lawe how our lorde was gone in to Galiſee.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:5702:10"/>
               <p>ANd as they were i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this are ruaylyng they and ne entred in to theyr ſynagoge / &amp; amonge the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> there came one of the knyghres y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> kepte the ſepulcre &amp; to them he tolde ryght ſykerly y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> our lord Ieſu was not in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> monument. And anone the mayſters of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> law aſked hym where y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> they had done hym. And y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> knyght thus anſwered them and ſayd. As we kepte y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> graue the erth ſhoke / and than we ſawe veryly that an aun gell deſcended downe frome heuen and lyfted vp the ſtone from the monumente / and ſet hym there vpon / and his face was very bryghte / and his veſture was whyte as ſnowe / and for the grete drede that we had we laye as we were deed. Than we herde the au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gelt ſay vnto the women that were comen to the ſepulcre dyſmaye you not nor drede you not / for I knowe well that ye ſeke Ieſu that was crucyfyed / but Ido you to were that he is ryſen and is not here / for ye ſhall ſe hym in Galylee / as he ſayd to you before. And whan the prynces of the lawe herde this they ſayd to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kny<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ght. Is Ieſus than on lyue / we may not vyleue this that ye ſay. Than the knyght anſwered them. Ieſus hath done many myracies that ye haue well herde / &amp; ſene and ye byleue it not how ſhold ye than byleue vs but your owne demau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de is good / whan ye aſke yf Ie<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſu be on lyue / whome than ſayd y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Ie wes to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> knyght we ſhall yelde to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Ioſeph yf ye wyll yelde to vs Ie<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſu for we do you to were that Ioſeph is i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Barmathy Than ſayd y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> knyght / &amp; we do you to were that Ieſu is in Galilee ryſen fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> deth to lyfe / &amp; there they ſholde ſe hym. And whan y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iewes herde this they had gret drede / &amp; thus they ſayd among themſelfe / yf men here theſe wordes of theſe knyghtes they ſhal all byleue in Ieſu. Than they aſſembled them togyder &amp; gaue to
<pb facs="tcp:5702:10"/>the knyghtes treaſure / and thus they ſayd to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Go<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ye and ſay to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people as ye lay &amp; ſlepte his dyſcyples came pryuely by nyght &amp; ſtole y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> body of Ieſu / &amp; yf Py late knowe here of we ſhal excuſe you. Thus y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> knygh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes toke this treaſure &amp; proclamed as they co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded them / &amp; ſo theyr wordes were ſoone ſpred all aboute.</p>
               <p>THan came there thre men whiche y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hyght Fy nees / Abbas / and Leuy / theſe thre men came fro Galilee in to Ieruſalem and thus they ſayd to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prynces &amp; to all them y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> were in the ſynagoge. Syrs we haue herde &amp; ſene Ieſu whiche that ye crucified &amp; fyt and ſpeke to his dyſcyples vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of olyuete and there he preched to them &amp; ſayd. Go &amp; preche my name &amp; my goſpell thrugh out y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worlde / baptyſynge in the name of the fader / and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſone / and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy ghoſt And what ſo euer he be that wyl be baptyſed &amp; byleue in me he ſhall be ſaued / &amp; he that byleueth not ſhall be dampned. And whan y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prynces herde this they ſayde to theſe thre men. Men gyue prayſynge &amp; worſhyp to our lorde Ieſu and be a knowe yf this be true that ye haue harde and lene / &amp; theſe men ſayd all togyder w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> one voyce / by that lorde that is god of Abraham / of yſa ac / and Iacob / we ſawe Ieſuſy ttynge and prechyng to his dyſcyples / &amp; yf we couer this that we haue her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de and ſene we ſholde do grete ſyn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e. And anone y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pry<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces roſe vp and helde y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lawe in theyr handes / &amp; thus they ſaid to them. we conture you by the lawes of our lorde that ye kepe this counſeyle y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ye haue ſayd to vs of Ieſu / and ſo they gaue to theſe thre men grete trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure / and ſo they ſente thre knyghtes with them for to brynge them in to theyr owne countree / and that they ſholde nolenger abyde in Ieruſalem.❀</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:5702:11"/>
               <p>SO came there agrete aſſemble of comyns to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prynces / and thus they ſayd with a grete co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>playnt / what tokens are theſe that are befalle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in Iſra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>hell. Than Annas and Cayphas conforted the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; ſayd we ought not for to byleue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> knyghtes that kepte the ſepulcre wherin that Ieſu was put / they ſayd to vs that they had ſene an aungell lyfte vp y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtone from the monument / and peraduenture his dyſeyples ſayd to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> knyghtes / and we wote well y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> they gaue to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> knygh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes grete treaſure for to ſay thus / and ſo ſtale awaye his body / thus men ought to byleuevs rather than the dyſcyples that gaue the knyghtes grete treaſure for to bere falſe wytneſſe. Than aroſe Nychodemus vp and thus he ſayde to them / ye haue herde what theſe thre men haue ſayd &amp; ſworne vpon the lawe that they ſawe Ieſu ſytte and ſpeke to his dyſcyples vpon the mount of olyuete / and there he ſtyed vp to heuen. And ye wote well that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcrypture telleth vs that Elye y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy prophete was rauyſſhed in to paradyce / and wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aſked his dyſcyple Elyze we where that his fader Elye was / he anſwered rauyſſhed in to heuen. &amp; than they ſuppoſed well y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> he was rauyſſhed by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy goſt &amp; lefte hym ſomwhere on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes of Iſraell / &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore they ſayd let vs ſeke ſome men that may go and ſe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke hym. So they wente and ſought thre dayes &amp; thre nyghtes / but they coude not fynde Elye / &amp; therfore I counfeyle you for to ſende ſome for to ſeke y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes of Iſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ahell / for parauenture y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy ghoſt had rauyſſhed Ieſu / &amp; parauenture he may be founde / let vs than do penaunce for the treſpaſſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> we haue done. This cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeyle of Nychodemus was pleſynge to all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iewes &amp; ſo they ſent men for to ſeke our lorde Ieſu / but they myght not fynde hym in no place. And wan theſe men
<pb facs="tcp:5702:11"/>were repayred agayne they ſayd to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> te wes / we haue lought Ieſu on euery hyll of Iſrael / &amp; in euery dale &amp; i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> euery place / but we can fynde hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> no where but we ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de Ioſeph in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cyte of Barmathy / &amp; wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pryn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces herd this they were wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ders ioyful &amp; mery / &amp; they gloryfyed god y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Ioſeph was fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de / &amp; ſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fewes &amp; may ſters of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lawe aſſembled the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> togyder / &amp; keſt amonge the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> how they myght ſpeke to Ioſeph / &amp; ſo they made letters which ſayd thꝰ. Peas be w<hi rend="sup">e</hi> the &amp; alſo w<hi rend="sup">e</hi> them y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> be w<hi rend="sup">e</hi> the / we knowe well y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> we haue ſpn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ed in god &amp; in the / &amp; therfore fader Ioſeph come to vs ſyth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> we haue knowyng y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> we haue greuouſly ſyn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ed &amp; treſpaſt flyenſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> &amp; hugely we meruayle of thy delyuerau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce &amp; takynge away fro vs. we knowe well y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> we co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſpyred euyl cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſeyle ayenſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> but goddelyuered y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fro vs / but peas be w<hi rend="sup">e</hi> the fader Ioſeph worſhyppes of all people.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ How y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iewes choſe .viii men that were Ioſephes trendes to deſyre hym to come to them.❀</head>
               <p>THan they choſe. viii. men which that were fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des to Ioſeph &amp; ſayd whan ye come to Ioſeph ſalue hym in peas / &amp; do to hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> gretynges in our behal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe &amp; delyuer to hym theſe letters. So theſe men went forth to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cyte of Barmathye / and wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they came afo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re Ioſeph they ſalued hym &amp; grete hym &amp; delyuered to hym y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> letters And wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Ieteph had reed theſe letters he ſayd thus, Bleſſyd be my lorde god that hath coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red me with his wynges / and alſo bleſſyd myght he he that hath ſaued me from all myſcheue. Tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Ioſeph ladde all theſe men in to his place / and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> nexte day af<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes he toke his hors and rode with them in to Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem. And whan y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iewes w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the mayſters of the lawe
<pb facs="tcp:5702:12"/>herde tell of his comynge they wente worſhypfully ayenſt hym / and wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they mette with hym they ſayd thus to hym. Peas be at thy comynge fader Ioſeph / &amp; Ioſeph anſwered. The peas of our lorde be to all his true people. And than y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mayſters of the lawe with all the people they kyſted Ioſeph. And Nychodemus led Ioſeph in to his hous. Than the nexte daye after An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas and Cayphas and Nychodemus ladde Ioſeph in to the temple / &amp; thus they ſayd to hym. Fader Ioſeph gyue vs knowlege and to god this temple of that we ſhall are of you / fader Ioſeph ye knowe well y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ye ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed the body of Ieſu / and fader ye knowe well y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we ſhette you inpryſon &amp; we coude not fynde you therin &amp; therfore tell vs what befell there Thau Ioſeph an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered &amp; ſayd what ye dyde ſhe its me in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> eldſe pry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſabbot daye as I was in my<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> or y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap> &amp; prayers y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> place was ſpredde aboue me w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> huge lyght as me thought feont the foute partyes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ayre / and ſo Ilyfte vp my heed and ſawe mylorde Ieſuſtande faſt by me ſhynyng with grete clereneſſe / &amp; ſo for dre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de that I had Ife<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dovone flatte to the goou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de. Than my bleſſyd lorde Isſaher<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> me by the h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> de and ly<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> me vp from the groſide and waſſhed my fate kyſſyn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> me and thus he ſayd to me. Broder Ioſeph y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> are elens by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> water of thy fayth / for thy ſynnes ben rel eaſed &amp; forgyuen / and theres my frenbe haue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>od<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſet holde me &amp; knowe what I am and ſo Ioyde behold <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> him &amp; ſayd any may ſter Elye and he anſwated agay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne &amp; layd. I am not Elyt but I am Ioſucryſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the thou buryed worſhypfully / &amp; than fayd I to hym Lorde ſhewe me thy monument where Ibaryed the And than my forde Ieſu hente me by the hande and ladde me to the monumente / and there he ſhewed me
<pb facs="tcp:5702:12"/>the precyous Syndonia that I wounde hym in. And than I knewe verrly that he was my lorde Ieſu / &amp; ſo I fell downe and worſhypped hym / and ſayd my lorde Ieſu bleſſyd myght thou be that arte come hyder for to vyſyte me / &amp; thrughe thy grace haſt delyuered me &amp; ſo he helde me by the hande and ladde me to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cyte of Barmath ye. And than he ladde me in to my place and ſayd to me. Ioſeph broder peas be with the / and loke y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thou go not out of thy place theſe .xi. dayes / for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes ſhall do many grete dyſtreſſes to many of my fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des / &amp; now ſhall I go to my dyſcyples &amp; ſpeke to them of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaluac yo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the worlde. And whan he had ſayd y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> worde he vanyſſhed awaye from me / and wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pryn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces of the lawe &amp; other Iewes herde this that Ioſeph layd / they were hugely abaſſhed / &amp; for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> grete drede y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they had they fell downe to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> erthe / and ſo they cryed and ſayd. what tokens are theſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> are befallen in Iſra hell the knyghtes that kepte y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſepulcre bere wytneſſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they lawe an aungell dyſcende downe from heue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / &amp; that Ieſu was ryſen frodeth to lyfe / and that he ſhal he ſene in Galelee. And we knowe welthat Ieſu was a man / and his fader and moder we knowe well / both Ioſeph and Marye. What may we ſaye here ayenſt. Than ſayd a Iewe whoſe name was Leuius. I kno<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>we well the begyunynge of Ieſu / for I haue ben mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>the with them / for vpon a tyme as I was in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> temple in myn offrynges and orylons / that ſame tyme ſaynt Symeon toke hym in his armes / and thus he ſayd to hym. My lorde godlette now thy ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t come to the in peas / for myn eyen haue ſene thy helth that thou or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deyned or ony people was. Than ſayd y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iewes. Let vs ſende for theſe thre men that ſayd that they ſawe Ieſu ſpekynge to his dyſcyples vpon the mounte of
<pb facs="tcp:5702:13"/>of yuete. And ſo they ſente for theſe thre men / and wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they were come<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for them they ſayd truly that god of heue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was on lyue / and that we ſawe berely how that Ieſuſtped in to henen afore all his dyſeyples.</p>
               <p>THa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſwered Annas &amp; cayphas / out law ſayth that by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wordes of two or thre is ſuffycyent wytneſſe / what may we ſayhereto / we know well y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Enocke pleaſed god / and was rauy flhed in to heue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fepulchre of Moyſes myght neuer be fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Pylate delyuered to vs this Ieſu whiche we bere w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> frourgꝭ &amp; crowned hym w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thornes / &amp; after warde was crut y<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyed / &amp; ſmote hym in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſyde w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a ſpere &amp; Ioſeph buryed his body in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſepulcre / whiche y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> now bereth wytnes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he is on lyue. And theſe men ſay y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they ſawe hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſtye vp in to heue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / &amp; tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Ioſeph tolde another gret meruay le y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> there roſe vp many deed bodyes out of the yr gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues I wote well y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſome me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haue ben in Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / which y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> myſbyleuers haue not ſene / &amp; we know well y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſaynt Simeon receyued Ieſuin his atmes in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> temple whiche was a full holy man / this Simeon had two ſones whoſe names were Gariꝰ &amp; Leuicius &amp; we were at theyrdeth &amp; at theyr but yenge. Go now and ſerche the yr graues / but I wote well they be not there / but they be in y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> cyte of Barmathye in orylons &amp; ſpeke to noma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / but kepe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſtyll as though they were deed / &amp; therfore let vs go to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> worſhyp / &amp; brynge them to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> temple / &amp; wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>iured them pars uenture they wyll tell vs ſomwhat of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reſurtete you of Ieſu / and how that he roſe from deth to lyfe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ How the Iewes wente to ſeke two deed men that were ryſen from dethe to lyfe in Barmathye.</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:5702:13"/>
               <figure>
                  <head>
                     <list>
                        <item>Cayphas.</item>
                        <item>Annas.</item>
                        <item>Earius.</item>
                     </list>
                  </head>
               </figure>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Nd ſo al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> iewes &amp; mayſters of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> law went to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> graues of theſe two bredren / &amp; ſo they fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not there. And anone they wente to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cyte of Barmathy which was .xl. myle fro Ieruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / &amp; ſo they fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>lyuynge. Than they kyſſed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; led them w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> them to Ieruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with grete worſhyp / &amp; tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they lad the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to theyr ſynagoge / &amp; wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they had ſhet y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dores ſurely they toke theyr lawꝭ / &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fured the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lawe of Iſraell / &amp; by god adonay yf y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> theylyued / &amp; yf y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Ieſu was god of Iſrael y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> reyſed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Gariꝰ &amp; Leuiciꝰ herd this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>iuracyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / they loked vp togyder in to heue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they made ſygnes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy croſſe on the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / &amp; than they ſayd &amp; ſpake / gyue vs ꝑ thement &amp; ynke / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we may wryte thyngꝭ y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we haue
<pb facs="tcp:5702:14"/>herde and ſene / and ſo they gaue to them bothe ynke and perchement / and whan they were ſet they wrote bothe togyder and ſayd thus.</p>
               <p>¶ Our lorde Ielucryſt is reſurreccyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deth &amp; lyfe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> byleue vpon hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / ſuffre vs to ſay y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſecretes of thy dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyne mageſte that y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> dydeſt in hell by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deth of thy ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly croſſe / for we be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>iured by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> for to ſpeke of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> / y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> haſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded to thy ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t by Myghell thyn archau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gel y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we ſhold tel y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſecretes of thy dyuyne mageſte what y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> dydeſt in hell after thy holy reſurreccyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as we were w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> our forne faders in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> grete preuy depnes of derknes there came a grete bryghtneſſe as it had ben a beme of lyght fro y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſonne / and y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> keſt alyght royall vpon vs / &amp; anone Adam y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> was our forne fader / and patryarkes &amp; prophetes roſe vp lyghtly &amp; ſayd. This is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lyght of hym y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> behyght vs for to ſende to vs endeles lyght and anone yſaac with an hyghe voyce began for to ſaye.</p>
               <p>¶ This is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lyght of our fader ſone of god as I ſayd here afore whan I was on lyue in the londe of zabulo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and neptalem ouer y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> flomiordan. The people that ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te iderkenes ſawe grete bryghtnes of lyght &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lyght was ſente to them that ſate in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſhadowe of deth that was there as it had ben a ſterre ſhynynge aboue vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs. And as we were in this Ioy and gladneſſe of this lyghte that ſhone vpon vs there came to vs our fader Symeon and thus he ſayd to vs with grete Ioye.</p>
               <p>¶ Gloryfye our lord god Ieſu cryſt our ſauyour whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che I receyued a chylde in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> temple / and toke hym in myne armes ſayenge thus / let now thy ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t paſſe for myn eyen haue ſene thy helth / whan all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> grete co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of layntes that were i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hell herde this they were wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ders Ioyful &amp; mery. And after came another ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to vs as it had be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> an heremyte / &amp; our forne fader aſked
<pb facs="tcp:5702:14"/>hym what he was / &amp; he anſwered agayne and ſayd I am a voyce of a prophete of an hye co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany for I haue gone afore y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> face of his comynge / &amp; alſo to make redy y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> way of his comynge / and to gyue helth &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nynge to his people in the remyſtyon of theyr ſynnes / &amp; wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Iſawe hym come tome I was fulfylled with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy ghoſt / and thus I ſayd / ſe the lawbe of god &amp; be holde hym that doth awaye ſynne of the worlde / and hym I haue baptyſed in the Flomiordan &amp; vpon hym I ſawe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy ghoſt delcende in lykenes of a doue. And than I herde a voyce y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> came fro heuen ſayenge thus / this is my ſone in whom grete pleſynge is vnto me. And now I am come before hym to you to ſhe we to you the ſone of god is come fro he yght for to delyuer vs y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſyt in derkeneſſe / and in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſhado we of dethabydyng his mercy. Whan y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Adam our forne fader was baptyſed anone he ſayd to Seth his ſone. Tell to thy thyldren &amp; to patryatkes &amp; prophetes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the aungell layd to the whan I ſente the to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gates of paradyce that y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſhol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt praye our lorde god y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he wolde ſende to me by his au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geil of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fruyte of lyte / &amp; alſo of the oyle mercy for to anoynte withall my membrs ſuche tyme y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I was fulfylled ful of malady &amp; ſekeneſſe. Than Seth ſtarte vp &amp; ſayd with an hygh voyce. As I was at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gates of paradyce prayenge our lorde god of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> oyle of mercy our lorde ſente Myghell his archau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gell ſayage thus vnto me our lorde god hath ſent me to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> / trauayle not for to haue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> oyle of mercy to anoynte w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Adam thy fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der / Ido do the to were thou mayſt not haue it vnto the laſt day be complete of .v. M. and .v. C. yere. And than ſhall the ſone of god Ieſu cryſte come in to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worlde for to reyfe the body of Adam thy fader / and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bodyes of the holy ſayntes patriarkes and prophetes / &amp; than
<pb facs="tcp:5702:15"/>ſhall he be baptyſed in flomiordan / &amp; wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he cometh out of the water than ſhall he anoynt with the oyle of mercy all thoſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhall byleue in hym / &amp; than ſhall the ſone of god go downe to hell and lede Adam thy fader in to paradyce to the tree of lyfe &amp; mercy. whan the pa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tryarkes &amp; prophetes herde this y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whiche Seth had ſayde / they made than grete Ioye &amp; gladneſſe / and as they made this grete Ioye Sathan the prynce of hell and mayſter of deth ſayd to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mayſters of turmentry Make the redy for to receyue Ieſu Cryſte the which that gloryfyeth hym ſelf to be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſone of almyghty god and yet he is man that dredeth deth / for he dyd ſay my ſoule is heuy aye<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt deth. And this Ieſu hath wrought many heuyneſſes &amp; euylles ayenſt me for them that I made blynde croked &amp; lame &amp; mezel he hath made hole by his worde. And alſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deed that I haue brought to the he hath reyſed to lyfe. Than the prynce of turmen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try anſwered to Sathan what is he y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is ſomyghty by his worde / and thou ſayeſt that he is man that dredeth deth / al that euer were myghty in erth thou haſt brought the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to my bo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des / &amp; yf he be ſo myghty in man hode as thou ſayeſt. I ſaye to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> he is ſo myghty in dy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uynyte y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we may neuer reſyſt agaynſt hym / &amp; yf y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> he ſayd that he dradde deth I ſaye to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> that he wyll dyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue the and ouercome y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> at all tymes / &amp; than anſwe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red Sathan to the mayſters of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tourme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>try and ſaid Why dredeſt thou for to receyue myne aduerſary and thyne I haue made the Iewes for to be ayenſt hym / and I haue made redy the rodde that he ſhal be ſmyte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with / and I haue made redy y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tree that he ſhal be cru<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyfyed on / &amp; thre nayles for to faſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hym therto / and I haue made a drynke with azel &amp; gall that he ſhal drynke / and I tell the that he ſhall be deed anone / &amp; I ſhall
<pb facs="tcp:5702:15"/>brynge hym redely to the. Than anſwered the prynce of the tourmentrye / this that thou ſayeſt y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he by his myght hath taken fro me them that were deed / what hopeſt thou he may be y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> dothe ſuche mayſtryes by his worde. I dred me perauenture that this was he that toke away Lazer from me and reyſed hym that was thre dayes deed / whome that I helde boſide in my pry<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſon / and hym he yelded to lyfe by his worde. Than an ſwered Sathan and ſayd. I do the to were that he is the ſame Ieſu. And whan y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prynce of turmentry her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de this he ſayd to Sathan I co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ture the by thy vertue &amp; myne that thou brynge hym nothere to me / for wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I herde the commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dement of his worde I trembled and ſhoke for dred and all my fell ſergeau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes with me ſo that we ne myght kepe Lazer / but he fle we fro vs ſo ſwyfte as it had ben an Egle out of the bondes that we had hym in / and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> erth that he laye in deed vndyd and yelded hym quycke fro hym / weneſt thou Satha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for to holde ſuche a lord that toke his ſeruaunt fro vs maugre vs all by the vertue of his worde / were y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> wel this without doubte yf thou bryng hym hyder that is ſo myghty to ſaue all mankynde / he wyl put vs hens I ſay Sathan and all tho that be ſhytte in our pryſon and ſtrayned by their ſynne in our bo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des by hym they ſhal be delyuered and brought vnto euerlaſtynge lyfe And as they ſpake thus togyder there came a voyce as it had be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thonder of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy ghoſt / and thus he ſayd. (At tollite portas pricipes vr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>as) ye pry<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces of deth vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloſe your gates / for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pry<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of glory ſhal entre therin And whan the prynce of hell herde this voyce he ſayd to ſathan / go hens fro vs &amp; thou be myght yo fyght / go fyght with hym that is kyng of glorye. And ſo hel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>keſt ſathan fro hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / &amp; tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſayd to his fell ſergeau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes
<pb facs="tcp:5702:16"/>ſhyt myghtely your gates with yren barres &amp; fyght myghtyly / &amp; withſtande hym myghtly that the kyng of blyſſe come not herein / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> our ſtrength be not taken frome vs / and we be put vnto endeleſſe ſoro we. And wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſayntes herde this they ſayd with an hyghe voyce to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deuylles and to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prynces of turmentynge wretches vndo your gates and let the kyng of glorye come in. Than ſayd Dauyd y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prophete / prophecyed I not whan I was lyuynge in erth &amp; ſayd thus (Quia hec eſt dies qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fecit dn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s exultemus et letemur in ea That is to ſay / this is the day y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> god made / therin we may be blythe and glad. And after hym ſayd yſaye to all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayntes. Sayd I not whan I was lyuyng that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deed ſholde be lyfte vp &amp; the bodyes that lye in gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues ſholde be reyſed vp frode the to lyfe / &amp; that they y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> be in erth ſhold be full of Ioye / &amp; yet I ſaye now more ye cayt yues of deth and hel where is now your pryde where is now youre vyctorye. whan y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayntes herde yſaye ſay theſe wordes / they ſayd all at ones to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pry<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce of hel. Vndo your gatꝭ wretches for ye be but take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de &amp; may not helpe your ſelfe. Tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> came y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> voyce y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſeconde tyme ſayenge thus (Attollite portas vr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>as) And whan that hel herd this voyce come two tymes he anſwered vnauyſedly thus (Quis e<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>iſte rex glorie that is to ſay / what is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kynge of blyſſe. And than an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered Dauid ſayenge thus. I knowe well y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> voyce by his wordes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy ghoſt. For I ꝓphecyed it afore, and now I ſay to the hell (Du<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s deus fortis etpotens dn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s pote<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> prelio / ipſe eſt rex glorie) this is for to ſay. Our lorde god ſtronge and myghty / &amp; myghty in ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayle / he is kyng of glorye (Et ipſe de celo i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> terram aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pexit vt audiret gemetꝰ co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>peditoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vt ſolueret filios intere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) That is to ſaye / that bleſſyd lorde behel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de
<pb facs="tcp:5702:16"/>fro heuen to erthe to here y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> waymentynge of them that are in bondes / and that he ſholde vnbynde y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chyl dren that were brought to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deth to be ſlayne / &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thou vylſayne ſtynkynge hole vndo thy gates y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> the kynge of blyſſe may come in.</p>
               <p>ANd as Dauyd had ſayd this to hell / came vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them the gloryous deſyred kynge of glorye in fourme of man / &amp; enlumyned all the derkeneſſe of hell with the gloryous bryghtneſſe of his gloryous face / &amp; all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gates &amp; ſhyttyngꝭ with yren barres &amp; boltes all to braſte in his holy comynge / &amp; all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tell fendes made hym ſpace and waye. And wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayntes ſawe Ieſu our ſauyour come with au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gelles / they were abaſſhed of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> grete Ioye ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> theyne durſte ſpeke / but w<hi rend="sup">c</hi> grete and ſofte herte they ſayd thus. Our lord god &amp; our ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uyour y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> arte come to vs kyng of glorye to delyuer vs out of the bondes fro theſe falſe felons / &amp; bleſſyd be thy name / for now ſhall we be made hole. Than came our lorde Ieſu &amp; braſt all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bondes that we were bounde with / &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded that we ſholde be delyuered of all anguyſſhes from that tyme forwarde. And whan the prynce of hell with all his fell ſergeau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes ſawe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te bryghtneſſe / they had than huge ſorowe and drede. Than .x. prynces of hell roſe vp of theyr ſetes w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> huge full roryng and cryenge / &amp; ſayd thus with grete way mentyng. O Ieſu how we be ouercome by the / what man arte thou that reyſeſt thy requeſt ayenſt god vn knowyng vs what arte y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> that brekeſt all our power what arte thou that arte ſo grete &amp; appered ſolytel in erth. what arte thou that was ſo meke &amp; lowly i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> erth &amp; now thou arte a pryncely fyghter in fourme of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; now kynge of glorye y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> was deed &amp; now thou lyueſt
<pb facs="tcp:5702:17"/>and now al creatures tremble and quake by the croſſe and by the deth / &amp; were buryed in a ſepulcre &amp; art dyſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cended downe to vs / all quyck creatures tre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ble &amp; qua<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke be thy deth / &amp; all the foure elementes ſhewed theyr tokens / &amp; now haſt thou delyuered al them that were deed &amp; dyſtroubled / &amp; put to myſchefe al our ful fel my hyſters. what arte y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> that haſt delyuered the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re dyſtreyned here amonge vs for theyr ſynne / &amp; haſte called them agayne to theyr fyrſt fraunchyſe. what ar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te thou that gyueſt lyght to them that are blynde by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bryghtneſſe of thy godhede. And tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> were in hel cryed with one voyce and ſayd. A what arte thou y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te ſo myghty a man &amp; ſo clere in mageſte ſhynynge w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> out blame &amp; clene of erthly ſynne / what arte thou that entreſt in to our regyon &amp; countree without drede / and doubteſt no poynt of turmentynge but haſt fro vs all tho that were ſtreyned in our bondes / parauenture y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> arte that Ieſu y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> our nrynce Sathan ſayd to our pryn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces that thou ſholdeſt take to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> al the power of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worl<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de by thy deth of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> croſte. Than our lorde Ieſu Cryſte toke Sathan and bounde hym and del yuered hym in to hell to the prynce of turmentry. Than be helde Sa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>than ſaynge thus to hym. A <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>chucnk<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>prynce of perdycyon Belſabub with thy thre hedes / lyer vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gelles of god why haſt thou do this falſe dede. A what a dyf<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fpoylynge thou behyghteſt vs whan y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> let hym falle to ſuche a dede / what harme thou dyd to vs wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou let the kynge of glorye be crucyfyed. A thou fals Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than thoune woteſt what thou haſt done / for this Ie<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſu hath enlumyned all the derkeneſſe of deth with the clereneſſe of his dyuynyte / and hathe now broken all the gates of our depe pryfons / and vnbounde all that were therin / &amp; they that were i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our turmentryes they
<pb facs="tcp:5702:17"/>ſcorne vs &amp; by theyr prayers we ſhal euer after be ouer come y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> neuer afore durſt ſaye one worde ayenſt vs / &amp; now ſhal neuer none of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kynde come amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge vs but euer ſhal lede vs where they wyl / y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> neuer afore durſt do aye<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt vs / &amp; now are they fulfylled ful of merualoꝰ Ioye by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prayſynge of theyr lorde god. A thou prynce of all ſhrewdnes / and fader of all telonyes why haſt thou done thus / how durſt y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> do ſuche a lorde be crucy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyed / for now be all tho that were in dyſpayre fro y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> be gynnyng vnto this tyme now in helth &amp; in endleſſe ly te. And we ſhall neuer here theyr grudgy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge gronyng nor wepynge. A thou fell Sathan all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ryches y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou haddeſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>quered by thyn apple i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> paradice / y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> haſt now loſt by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tree of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> croſſe / and all thy Ioye is peryſſhed whyle that y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> haſt crucyfyed hym y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> was ayenſt the / &amp; wete thou well that thou ſhalte ſuffre tormentry end leſly in myne horryble pryſon. A thou fals curſed Sa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>than auctor of deth &amp; fader of pryde thou ſholdeſt fyrſt haue enquyred his cauſe: &amp; yf he had be worthy dethe and yf thou haddeſt founde noo cauſe of dethe in hym thou ſholdeſt haue lefte hym on lyue / but thou founde no faute nor cauſe to crucyfye hym / and bycauſe thou were ſo hardy to crucyfye hym / thou arte y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cauſe that he is entred in to our regyon / and woteſt thou what y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> haſt done. I ſaye to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thou haſt all forlorne &amp; we wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches ſhall dwell in turmentrye y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> euer ſhal laſt as hel And as Sathan ſpake thus came the kynge of blyſſe and thus he ſayd to hel. Thou prynce of hell Sathan thy power ſhall be endleſly too dwell here in ſtede of Adam and his chyldre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; all my ryghtfull people. and than our bleſſyd lorde ſpredde forth his ryght hande &amp; ſayd come to me my holy &amp; al that haue myn ymage &amp; my lykeneſſe whiche were dampned to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deth by the
<pb facs="tcp:5702:18"/>fruyte of the apple &amp; by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deuyll / &amp; now may ye well ſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the deuyll is dampned by the tre &amp; by the croſſe / &amp; anone all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayntes aſſembled the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> togyder vnder our lordes hande. Than our lorde toke Ada<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by the ryght hande &amp; ſayd thus to hym. My peas be with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> and all my ryghtfull chyldre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / &amp; all my holy ſayntes / &amp; tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our <abbr>fornfad</abbr> fell downe on his knees afore our bleſſyd lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de wepy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge for Ioye / &amp; thus he ſayd (Exaltabote dn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e qm<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuſcepiſti me no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> delectaſti i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> imicos meos ſuꝑ me. Dn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e deꝰ meꝰ clamaut ad te et ſanaſti me deduriſti ab iteris aiam mea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſanaſti me a deſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tibꝰ in lacu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) This is to ſaye. My lorde I ſhall enhaunce y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> for that thou haſt taken me / for y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ne haſt ſuffred myne enymyes to be aboue me. My lorde god I haue crted to the &amp; thou haſt made me hole / y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> haſt brought my ſoule out of hel &amp; haſt ſaued me from them y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> are fallen in the depneſſe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lake. And than al the ſayntes fell downe to our lor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des fete ſayenge all with one voyce to our lorde god / y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> arte come to vs byer of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worlde / bleſſyd be thy name as thou ſhe weſt to vs by the holy lawes &amp; by the holy prophetes / thou bought vs agayne by thy holy croſſe and y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> arte come downe to vs by thy holy vertue for to drawe vs fro deth / &amp; fro y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> horryble paynes of hel / and tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our bleſſyd lorde lyfte vp his ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de &amp; made y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſygne of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy croſſe on Adam and on his holy ſayntes. And ſo he toke Adam by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ryght ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de &amp; ſtyed out of hel vp in to the ayre &amp; all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayntes folowed hym. Than kyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge Dauyd ſayd with an hygh voyce (Cantate dn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>oca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> quia mirabilia fecet) That is to ſay. Synge to our lord god a newe ſong / for he hath wrought mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uayles (Ethec eſt gloria oibus ſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ctis eius) this is to ſay / bleſſyd be god for thy grete Ioy to all his ſayntes Than after Dauyd ſaid Micheas (Quis deꝰ ſicut tu
<pb facs="tcp:5702:18"/>domine auferens iniquitatem &amp; tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſgredie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s peccata<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>et nunc continens in teſtimonio tram tua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. &amp;c) That is for to ſay. Whois ſuche a lord as our lorde Ieſu cryſt is puttynge away al euylles of ſynne / and after hym ſayd Abacuk the prophete. Thou comeſt out w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> helth vnto thyn humble people for to delyuer all thy frendes from all ſorowes dyſeaſes and trybulacyons. And tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> after hym ſayd all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy ſayntes w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> one voyce. Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyd myght thou be that cometh i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the name of our lorde Ieſu cryſt / for thou arte Ioye and alſo blyſſe vnto all thy true people (Alleluya) And than all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prophetes pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nounced all theyr prophecyes that they had ſhewed in erth with grete pleaſynge to our lorde god. And than all the ſayntes ſayd / this is oure lorde god that ſhall gouerne vs without ende. Alleluya.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ Howe our lorde ledde all his holy ſayntes in to the Ioyes of paradyſe / &amp; of the thre men y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they mette.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Nd than our lorde toke Adam our forne fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der by the hande and ledde hym in to para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyſe and al his holy ſayntes with hym / and them he delyuered to Myghell his archau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> gell / and he ledde them in to paradyſe where as is end leſſe Ioye. And wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they were entred in to paradyle there came ayenſt them two men of grete age and the ſayntes aſked them what they were / and how it my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ght be that they were there ſo bodyly and had not ben with them in hell. Than one of them anſwered and ſayd I am Enocke that by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worde of god am tranſla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted hyder / &amp; he that is with me here is Elias teſbytes whiche was brought hyder in a brennynge chayre / &amp; yet ſuffred we no deth / but we are kepte to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> comyng
<pb facs="tcp:5702:19"/>of Antecryſt to fyght with hym w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wordes &amp; toke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of our lorde god / and of hym we ſhall be ſlayne in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cyte of Ieruſalem / &amp; thre dayes and a halfe after we ſhall ryſe fro deth to lyfe / &amp; be taken vp in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſkyes. And as Enocke tolde this to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayntes / there came to them a man berynge vpon hym y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſygne of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy croſſe. And whan all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayntes ſawe hym they ſayd to hym what man may thou be that haſt here y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lykenes of a thefe / and why bereſt thou the ſygne of the holy croſſe. And than this man anſwered vnto them and ſayd / forſoth ye ſay truly that I was a thefe / &amp; many curſed de des dyd I in erth. And therfore the Iewes crucyfyed me with our lorde Ieſu / and whan I ſawe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſterynges of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> elementes in his paſſyon I byleued that he was ſauyour of the worlde / and maker of all creatures / &amp; kyng almyghty / tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſayd I to hym / lord haue mercy on me / and haue me in mynde wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou comeſt in to thy kyngdome. And anone that bleſſyd lorde toke my prayer / and ſayd to me. This day ſhalte thou be with me in paradyce. And than he toke me the ſygne of the holy croſſe / and ſayd to me / bere this ſygne with the &amp; go to paradyce. And yf the aungell that is keper of pa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>radyce wyll not ſuffre y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> toentre in / ſhe we hym the ſygne of the croſſe / and ſaye to hym y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Ieſucryſt whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che that was now crucyfyed ſente me to the / &amp; whan I had ſayd this to the aungell / anone he vndyde y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ga<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes and ledde me i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to paradyſe / and ſet me on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ryght ſyde ſayenge thus to me / ſuffre and holde y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> here a ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell whyle / for Adam whiche is fader of all mankynd with all this chyldren and all the fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des of god ſhal co<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me hyder by the vertue of cryſtes paſſyon. And whan the holy ſayntes as patryarkes &amp; prophetes had her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de theſe wordes of this thefe than they ſayd al w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> one
<pb facs="tcp:5702:19"/>voyce. Bleſſyd be our lorde god almyghty endleſſe fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of mercy that ſuche grace hath gyuen to ſynners &amp; brought vs to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Ioye of paradyſe &amp; in to the paſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re of delyght and to endleſſe Ioye. Amen.</p>
               <p>THeſe are the holy ſecretes of the dſuynyte that we haue ſene I Garius &amp; my broder Leuiciꝰ but our lorde god wyll ſuffre vs no lenger to tell and ſhe we vnto you the ſecretes of his dyuyn yte / for ſaynt Myghell the archaungell ſayd to vs / ryſe &amp; go in to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cyte of Ieruſalem / and be there in prayers &amp; gloryfye the holy reſurreccyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of our lorde Ieſu cryſt with your bretherne that roſe with you / and that ye ſpeke to no perſone / but be you as domme vnto the tyme that our lorde ſhall ſuffre you for to ſhew the ſecretes of his dy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uynyte / and ſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy aungell ſaynt Mychaell co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ded vs to goo to flomiorda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to a place there that many are ryſen w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> vs in wytneſſe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reſurreccyon of our lorde Ieſu cryſt. Our lorde god hath grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted vs thre dayes to be in Iheruſalem &amp; holde there y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy palke of our lorde god with our frendes / &amp; alſo that we ſhal be bapt yſed in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> flomiordan eche of vs / at y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> tyme ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kynge whyte ſtooles. And thus ſaynt Myghell com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſided vs y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we ſholde be in oryſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cyte of Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mathye / and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> we ſholde ſhe we to you theſe holy ſecre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes / and therfore gyue prayſynge to our lorde god / &amp; be a know of your defaute / and do penau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he maye haue mercy vpon you. Now peas be with you of our lorde Ieſu cryſt that is lauyour of vs all Amen.❀</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ How Nychodemus and Ioſeph tolde to Pylate all that theſe two me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hadde ſayd / &amp; how Pylate treated with the prynces of the lawe.</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:5702:20"/>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Nd whan this ſerypture was wryten this Garins and Leuicius roſe vp / &amp; ſo Gartus delyuered the byll that he had wryten in to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> handes of Annas &amp; Cayphas &amp; to Gama<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>liel. And Leuicius gaue that he had wryten in to the handes of Nychodemus and Ioſeph of Barmathye / and anone they w<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ere tranſfygured and was no more ſene / for bothe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bylles were all one hande / as though one man had wryte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them both / and there was not one letter more in that one than in that other. And whan y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iewes &amp; mayſters of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> laws had reed theſe bylles &amp; vnderſtode the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they were hugely abaſſhed &amp; aſhamed And than they ſayd amonge them that forſothe Ieſu was very goddes lone / bleſſyd myghte he be endleſly for all thyng be reth wytneſſe therof. And anone after they went out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lynagoge. And than Nychodemus &amp; Ioſeph of Barmathy tolde all this vnto Pylate and than Pylate dyd wryte all that whiche was befalle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Ieſu / and of that the Iewes had ſayd of hym. And all theſe meruayles he dyd put i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his bokes. After that Pylate entred in to the Iewes / and afore hym aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mayſters of the lawe / as prynces &amp; byſſop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes. And than Pylate dyde commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de the gates and dores to be ſhette / and than he ſaid to them. Syrs it is done me to were that ye haue amonge you a newe ſto<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rye of grete ſcrypture the whiche ſcrypture I coueyte for to ſe / and therfore I charge you that it be brought in to my preſence. And whan it was brought to his pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſence / than ſayd he to them all. I coniure you all by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vertu of our lorde whiche that is fader and maker of all thynge that ye ne hyde no cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſeyle but for to ſay y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> trouth. Syrs ye knowe by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcryptures that is wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten here that Ieſu whiche y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> yecrucyfyed is very god<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des
<pb facs="tcp:5702:20"/>ſone / &amp; ſo it be houeth hym to come i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to this worlde for the helth of mankynde. And therfore I charge you that ye tell me what tyme y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> cryſt ſholde come by your lcrypture. Whan y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Annas and Cayphas were thus coniured / they charged &amp; commaunded that all ſholde go out of the temple ſaue Pylate and them two. And than they ſayd to Pylate good Iuge thou haſt ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iured vs that we muſt nedes ſhewe to the y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> trouth of this that thou haſt enquyred of vs. Syr vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tyme that we hadde crucyfyed Ieſu / we knowe not that he was goddes ſone / but we wende that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vertues that he wrought had ben done by ſome charme. Tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> made we vs aſſemble in this temple / &amp; here we dyd reherle all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vertues that he had wrought. And ſo there were many of our lynage that ſayd that they had ſene Ieſu after his paſſyon: and that they had herde hym ſpeke to his dyſcyples / &amp; they ſayd y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they lawe hym ſtye in to heuen / and we lawe alſo two men that Ieſu reyſed fro deth to lyfe which tolde vs many meruayles that Ieſu dyde in his dyenge &amp; after / &amp; that may ye were by thre ſcryptures y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> we holde in our handes / but our cuſtome is ſuche that we do worſhyp to ſtoryes y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> here afore in our ſynagoges / and ſo we fynde by wytneſſe of god in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fyrſt boke as it ſayth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Myghell the archaungell ſayd to Seth that was y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thyrde ſone of Adam whan .v. M. and .v. C. yere were co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plete tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſholde y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſone of god Ieſu cryſte come fro heuen / &amp; yet we abede his comyng &amp; paraue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ture this god of Iſra hell that ſayd to Moyſes that he ſholde make a hutche of wydnes in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lenght of two cubytes and an halfe / &amp; in the lenght of a cubyte and an halfe / &amp; theſe .v. cuby<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes we vnderſtande vy y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> olde teſtament that whan. v M. and .v. C yere is comen / than ſhall Ieſucryſt the
<pb facs="tcp:5702:21"/>ſone of god come in to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hutche / that is the wombe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mayde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Marye Thus our ſcrypture bereth wytnes of hym that ſhall be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſone of god / &amp; a kynge of the peo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple of Iſraell / but after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> paſſyon of Ieſu we &amp; oure prynces meruayled of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tokens &amp; wordes that were done by hym / &amp; ſo we loked our ſtoryes &amp; cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lynage downe to Ioſephs lynage / &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lynage of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry that was moder of Ieſu / &amp; ſo we haue accounted that fro y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> tyme that god made y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worlde and Adam the fyrſt man vnto Noes flode is two. M. &amp;. v C. yere And fro the flode to Abraham is thre. M. &amp;. v. C. yere / and fro Moyſes to Dauyd is .v. C. yere / &amp; fro y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mygracyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Babylone to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> incarnacyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Ieſu cryſt is foure. C. yere / and thus is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> accounte in all .v. M yere. All theſe thynges &amp; maruayles dyd pylate wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te for to be redde of all them y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſholde come after. and than Pylate wrote a letter to the cyte of Rome / and to Claudio the Emperour. &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>¶ Thus endeth Nychodemus goſpell.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>Imprynted at London in Poules chyrche yarde by me Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Skot. In the yere of our lorde god. M.CCCCC.xxix. the .vi. day of Apriell.</p>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>device of John Skot</figDesc>
                  <p>I S</p>
                  <p>IOHN SKOT</p>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:5702:21"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
